Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 30; L.S. 3p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Difficulties encountered in procuring Commodore Gillon's signature, in order that the goods purchased by Col. Laurens might be shipped to America; desires his advice and directions as to future proceedings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumesnil de St. Pierre, Henriette. Isigny
    Trouble taken by Franklin in ascertaining the circumstances of M. [John Lewis Dumesnil] de St. Pierre's death; has just received from Charleston all the necessary papers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Auer, Deacon M. Ebingen
    Received with joy Franklin's response in regard to the poor widow, Mme. Hōcklerin and her children; has followed his advice, and written to Mr. Richard Bache of Philadelphia. Begs that the enclosed letters may be forwarded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Cheminot, Charlotte de. Paris
    Greatly pleased at Franklin's acceptance of her invitation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Gregory, Lieut Stephen. Cherbourg
    Commissioned officer on board the "Confederacy" when she was captured by the English; has been ill ever since landing in France; begs that a place be found for him on board a man-of-war.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Ussant, -----, chevalier d'. Marmande
    Has received orders from M. de Castries to embark for further service in America. Asks for news of Mr. Searle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 3; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Fort, Marc. Marseilles
    Transcribes letter written July 30th. Concerning the capture of their ship "Elégante," and the indemnification promised them by Congress; desires Franklin's assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Mr. Trumbull had been discharged. At New Prison was refused admission to Mr. Gouverneur without an order from Mr. Knox, Lord Geo. Germain's Secretary. Encloses copies of his correspondence with Mr. Knox (1p.). Had no trouble in seeing Mr. Curson who thanks Franklin for his attention but neither he nor Mr. Gouverneur are in need of funds at present. Mr. Witherspoon discharged and soon to leave the country. Hopes for a speedy exchange of prisoners; some of the unfortunates have been three years in confinement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Damalix, --------. Paris
    Introducing his cousin who was taken prisoner at Savannah and who desires to see further service in the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Forwards letters received under cover from Robert Morris, Esq.; the messenger can be trusted in case Franklin wishes to send despatches by the "Delaware" or "Anne."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Account of money difficulties with a M. Dotun Le Sage; because of being a stranger, is obliged to settle with the villain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 9; L. in 3d P. 1p; Le Couteulx and Cie
    Enclosing three letters which have just arrived by way of London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Rayneval, Joseph Gérard de
    Acknowledging the Gazette; had already heard through M. le Chevalier de la Luzerne that the boasting of Mr. Cornwallis was of the same order as that of Admiral Rodney. In regard to the papers relating to passports, he supposes Franklin wishes him to lay them before the Peace Conference; thinks Mr. Robert Morris's letter should be communicated.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Lamarque, Fabre and Co. Paris
    Commodore Gillon owes them a large sum of money; according to Franklin's orders, went to M. Amelot who will await them the next day at twelve o'clock; begs that Franklin will have the goodness to be present while their sad situation is being explained. Adjoins memorial (4p.) concerning the orders taken for the clothing and equipment of the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Defay, Mlle ----. Paris
    Begging Franklin to visit his paper manufactory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Mr. [John] Adams convalescing from a severe illness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Montogomery, Dorcas. L'Orient
    Desires advice respecting the education of her son who may be placed in a school near Paris. Mr. and Mrs. [Richard] Bache and family were with them in July.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Lettsom, John Coakley. London
    Forwarding certain publications; Capt. [Jonathan] Carver's volume most interesting, treating of a country destined to form the hemisphere of freedom. Dr. Fothergill's works to be published in three volumes or one large quarto; anxious for any remarks of anectodes of their late amiable friend which Franklin may care to send him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Dusantoy Lescossois, -----. Rheims
    Wishes to know if it is true that American manufactories have been established at Nantes and other parts of France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Forwards the enclosed letters, as it is safer to transmit them through Franklin's hands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 14; L.S. 1p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Encloses a note of two books and desires that three complete sets be purchased on the Public Account and sent to him by three different conveyances.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John. Saint Ildefonso
    Concerning a complaint lodged against Mr.[David Salisbury] Franks that he left Cadiz without paying for his passage; this accusation unjust as Mr. Robert Morris engaged to pay the passage money in question.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 15; L.S. 1p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan. Bordeaux
    Introducing Mr. Stephen Willson lately arrived from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 15; L.S. 1p.; V. and P. French and Nephew. Bordeaux
    Encloses a letter for Mr. James Price, an American of distinction, lately arrived at l'Orient; remittances received for him despatched to their banker at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 15; L.S. 1p.; Amelot de Chaillou, Antoine-Jean. Versailles
    Acknowledging his favor of the 11th inst. in regard to the suspension requested by Messrs. Lamarque and Fabre; the account to be laid before the King with the details kindly entered into by Franklin, as to the cause of the difficulty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Carmichael, William. Saint Ildefonso
    Has heard with infinite satisfaction of Congress's refusal to accept Franklin's resignation, as well as the news of his appointment as a Peace Commissioner. Salary allowed him by Congress liberal but his expenses are numerous. Reasons why he has little opinion of the loan in Holland. Glad that the Court of France has engaged to replace the cargo of the "Marquis de la Fayette"; thinks the Americans have a way of demanding things as a right that they should solicit as a favor; cites Mr. Laurens as an example of this. Will send the memoirs of the Economical Society by first opportunity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 16; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Johonnot, Gabriel. Paris
    Unable to wait upon Franklin on account of preparations for his departure; asks for introductions to Mr. Williams and to French merchants at Nantes; desires a passport.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Hindman, John. Lisle
    Intelligence he collected while travelling through England; made his escape from a guard-ship in Plymouth where he had been detained a prisoner with Col. William Richardson. Account of the ships in the harbor at Plymouth and their destination. English papers speak of sending to America four regiments of infantry and one of horse; a mystery where they are to get them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafreté, Angélique-Michéle-Rosalie Jogues de Martinville. Paris
    The name of the person she recommended to Franklin for the position of Consul is M. Galart des Graux. Announces her intention of making a little trip into Normandy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Benard, ----- Letellieur. Rouen
    Concerning her son who served in the American navy for seven years and has only just returned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Mourier, — de. Cherbourg
    Concerning a bill of exchange drawn on Franklin by Mr. Nixon; greatly impressed with Franklin's generosity; offers to advance the money to Mr. Nixon.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. Obliged to him but the bill is paid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    The discharge of Major [William] Cowley, taken by the "Black Princess" and carried to Cherbourg. Board of Sick and Hurt agree to release Captain Manley in exchage. Number of prisoners released from Spain, of whom the Board takes no account. Prisons in England much crowded; upwards of seven hundred in confinement.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 20; L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Mr. [John] Adams still unable to attend to business; their share has been duly attended to.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 21; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Bidding good-bye to Franklin on her departure for a long journey.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781 September 22; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Castries, M de
    Sending a package and two letters which he had received for Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Johonnot, Samuel Cooper. Lyons
    Announcing his safe arrival.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] September 26; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hobart, George. Paris
    Desiring to know the fate of Mr. Pownall's letter to Mr. Bowdoin and Dr. Cooper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Lamarque, Fabre and Co. Paris
    Acknowledging Franklin's kindness in writing to the Minister on their behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David. Margate
    Suggesting a plan to prevent the horrid consequences of fire in opera and play-houses. Promises to send drawings and further details; efficacy of a fire-screen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Recommended to Franklin by the Comtesse d'Houdetot. Has been put in possession of the wherry in which the five Americans came over; sincerely sorry for poor Colonel [William] Palfrey; hopes that his successor will be equally capable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Jackson, Major William. Corunna
    Reports Mr. Gillon's violation of his contract and complains of the treatment accorded him and his companions by the former.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] September 27; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme. Villeneuve-le-Roy
    Is stopping at a country seat 30 leagues from Paris on her journey to Nice for her health. Describes the country and its beautiful scenery. Postscript by M. Pagin, a friend of Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Bouvinghausen, Maj. Gen. ----- de
    Has received a letter from America from Baron de Steuben; takes the liberty of sending his answer to Franklin's care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Porquet, P.M. Calais
    Sending him certain letters destined for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Mayo, Joseph. Paris
    Concerning the bill of exchange on M. de Chaumont which he has had protested.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781. September ?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hobart, George. Paris
    Sending him a book and a letter from Gov. Pownall.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Rayber, ---- chevalier de
    Desires to know if there is room in the service for more Frenchmen, who can furnish the best certificates and who are persons of family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Lovell, James. Philadelphia
    Introducing Mr. Gibbs, who desires to obtain Franklin's counsel in France, where he expects to spend some years; he is a son of Judge Gibbs and a grandson of Secretary [Josiah] Willard of whom he is a worthy descendant.
  - to Benjamin Franklin., 1781 October 4; L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    The vessel from New Haven bringing the accompanying packet brought also of hopes being high in America, on account of the expected arrival of M. de Grasse on that coast.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 4; LXI, 48.; Gillon, Alexander. Corunna
    Concerning the difference with [Major William] Jackson and [Col. John] Laurens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 4; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    His illness. Concerning the Commission appointed to negotiate peace; question of Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson accepting the trust; possible answer of the British to the articles which will serve as basis.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, IX, 81; Bigelow, VII, 299).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Desiring a commission for a fast-sailing brig under the command of Capt. James Tucker, purchased by some American seamen and officers lately arrived from England; intends to arm her as a letter of marque and put on board a small cargo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 4; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Veillard, Genevieve-Elisabeth Belamy
    Informed that Franklin has received bills of exchange drawn upon her; refuses to pay them unless Fanklin and his grandson consent to dine with her the following day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Janus, Baron de Freny. Paris
    Bitterly disappointed at being refused permission to enter the service of America; gave up his post in service of the Emperor and made this long journey, all in vain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    Introducing Capt. William Gibbons, whose ship was taken by the English on the voyage from Amsterdam to Boston; has just arrived from England and desires to consult Franklin on the best means of returning to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] October 6; A.L. 1p.; Brillion, Mme. Lyons
    Is disappointed at not having heard from Franklin and her friends at Passy. Leaving for Avignon in a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 8; L.S. 1p.; Woodmason, James. Leadenhall St
    Offering a new method of keeping copying paper damped.
    Printed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Sends his allegory in honor of the late Maria Theresa; his daughter finds great pleasure in Franklin's society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, c. 1781 October 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Poterat, Marquise de
    Asks for advice and assistance in the construction of her fire-place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Foulke, John. Leipsic
    Acknowledging his kindness to him during his stay in Paris. Coolness with which science is courted in Leipsic; inferiority of their schools to those in Paris; in no way superior to the young seminary which owes its birth to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Money due them. Amount and quality of tea forwarded. Desires Franklin's attention to Capt. Bell's request. Concerning the privateer, "Buccaneer," commanded by Capt [Hoysted] Hacker; importance of his not releasing his prisoners; thinks a few lines from Franklin would be efficacious.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Gillon, Alexander. Corunna
    Concerning the fulfilment of his contract and the payment of the debts of the State of South Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 14; L.S. 4p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Reasons which have determined him to educate his two elder sons, Robert and Thomas, in Europe; the bearer, Matthew Ridley, Esq., accompanies them to France and will see them placed at school in Geneva, if Franklin approves this choice; his intention to give them a liberal education. His veneration for Franklin's abilities and character must be his apology for drawing his attention from more important concerns; begs that he will assist Mr.Ridley with his good advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple. Orleans
    Much fatigued by the vehicle in which he travelled from Paris. Inquiries he made concerning Major Frank's whereabouts. Expects to continue his journey in the morning; the boatmen's demands very extravagant. Wants Franklin to make his excuses to Mr. and Miss Channing for not taking leave of them; knocked several times at their door without success.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 17; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Stewart, Mrs Mary
    Has written to Calais and to England for a copy of the work spoken of by Franklin. Sets out for Brussels tomorrow.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 17; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Montgomery, Dorcas
    Introducing her son; hopes to wait on Franklin herself in a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Franklin, William Temple. Chaumont
    Account of his journey from Orleans; his hospitable reception; Mme. de Chaumont and her children in good health; they depend on a visit from Franklin at Christmas; Mr. de Chaumont much beloved in that part of the world; all the family send their love and the beautiful Mme. Foucault accompanies hers with an English kiss.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 18; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Concerning a poor family called Beer who have come to Amsterdam with recommendations from Mr. Coffyn and Dr. Franklin; will do his best to get the father work of some kind. Relief he has furnished for a year past to American prisoners; no public money in his hands; cannot keep it up out of his own pocket; suggests other ways of continuing such a laudable work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 20; L.S. 1p.; Schaffer, John. Paris
    Is once more at liberty and hopes in a few days to repay his loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Renewing his application for a commission for the brig, "Sally," Capt. James Tucker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 20; L.S. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Writes on behalf of St. Jean, whose father M. de Crevecoeur is one of her oldest friends; begs Franklin to assist him in his desire to serve the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] October 20; A.L. 3p.; Brillon, Mme. Marseilles
    Her health is beginning to improve. Promises to write by turns to Franklin and Le Veillard. Has seen in the harbor a vessel called the "Comte d'Estaing" which was for sale.
    Postscript by M. Brillon. Hopes much from their stay at Nice, reputed to have the best climate in Southern France or Italy.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, October, 1906, 38.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] October 21; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hobart, George. Paris
    Sending him a pamplet by a former friend of Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Stewart, Mary. Brussels
    Has had an expensive law-suit which must be determined in her favor next fall; desires Franklin to assist her with £20
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Desires a certain kind of paper for a little volume which he is at present printing; hopes to offer Franklin a copy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 22; Mem. S. 1p.; Fizeaux, Grand Comp. Amsterdam
    Statement of account with the United States from May 16 to October 22, 1781.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 22; L.S. 4p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Asks for information concerning the duties and powers of a Peace Commissioner. Discusses demand made by Prince de Galitzin. Acknowledges Franklin's medical advice. Desires to know what disposition is to be made of the Continental goods left by Gillon and detained for the freight; from first to last was never consulted in the business; believes Col. Laurens has been imposed upon and that Gillon has Violated his contract with him; urges Franklin to send [Major William] Jackson to Amsterdam to finish the business, which has been cruelly mismanaged.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Carmichael, William. Madrid
    Introducing Mr. Boyetet, Spanish Consul-General for France, who will carry Franklin certain letters and papers; Mr.Boyetet's long residence in Spain; his knowledge of public affairs and the great assistance and kindness he has received from him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 23; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chalut and Arnoux, abbes de.
    Asking on behalf of M. de Chalut, Farmer-General, that Franklin dine with him on the 26th.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Mayo, Joseph. Paris
    Desiring to know M. de Chaumont's decision in regard to paying the bill of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Their good friend desires Franklin to dine with her the next day before going to Notre Dame for Te Deum.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 25; L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Testifying to Gillon's good character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Bohlen, Anna Sophia Susanna de (née Franklin)
    Claims to be Franklin's great niece through her father' father, John Franklin; has lost all her relatives; would like to come to Paris, but her means too narrow to permit of it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of August 6th. Explanation of how his account was reported to have been mixed up with Mr. [F.M.] Dana's. Question of his receiving a salary from the French Court; if this is refused him and Congress can remit him nothing, hopes at least he will be granted a free passage on one of the first frigates of war sent to America; reasons why it would go ill with him, were he taken prisoner by the English; would infinitely rather lie in the tower at Newgate than dishonor the United States by begging or borrowing the means for his subsistence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Stewart, Mary. Brussels
    Since, recommending the young man to Franklin, has heard some very disagreeable things about him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Avery, Jonathan. Kinsale Prison
    Surgeon on the brig, "Wexford"; captured by His Majesty's frigate "Recovery"; destitute of money and friends; offers to draw a bill on Samuel Huntington for whatever Franklin will advance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Adams, John. Amsterdam
    The ships which the "South Carolina" was to have taken under her convoy; advises that they be purchased and sent to America where their sale will far out-weigh the cost; urges that [Major William] Jackson be sent to Amsterdam to conduct the business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 28; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Montgomery, Dorcas
    Desires the honor of a letter for Geneva, as there is a probability of her leaving shortly for that place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Penet, P. Paris
    In his power to obtain a loan of 600,000 livres (tournois) for the use of the Commonwealth of Virginia, if Franklin will legalize his bonds for the State.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Major Cowley's release. Proposition made by the Board of Sick and Hurt as regards the exchange of prisoners; the last remittance used up; begs for a further supply.